My story begins right here actually in Rajasthan
تبدأ قصتي هنا تماما في الواقع في راجستان
about two years ago.
منذ حوالي سنتين.
I was in the desert, under the starry skies
كنت في الصحراء، تحت السماوات المليئة بالنجوم
with the Sufi singer Mukhtiar Ali.
مع المغني الصوفي مختيار علي.
And we were in conversation
وكنا نتحادث
about how nothing had changed
حول أنه لم يتغير أي شيء
since the time of the ancient Indian epic "The Mahabharata."
منذ زمن الملحة الهندية القديمة "المهابهاراتا".
So back in the day, when us Indians wanted to travel
لذلك في تلك الأيام عندما كنا نريد نحن الهنود السفر
we'd jump into a chariot and we'd zoom across the sky.
كنا نقفز في عربة ثم ننطلق مركزين نحو السماء.
Now we do the same with airplanes.
الآن نفعل الشيء ذاته مع الطائرات.
Back then,
في ذلك الوقت،
when Arjuna, the great Indian warrior prince,
عندما كان الأمير المحارب الهندي العظيم أرجونا،
when he was thirsty, he'd take out a bow,
عندما كان ظمئا كان يسحب قوسا،
he'd shoot it into the ground and water would come out.
ويقذفه نحو الأرض فيخرج الماء.
Now we do the same
الآن نفعل الشيء ذاته
with drills and machines.
عبر الحفارات والآلات.
The conclusion that we came to
الخلاصة التي توصلنا إليها
was that magic had been replaced
هي أن السحر اُستبدل
by machinery.
بالآلات.
And this made me really sad.
وجعلني ذلك حزينا فعلا.
I found myself becoming a little bit of a technophobe.
وجدت نفسي أصبح قليلا مثل الذي يرهب التقنية.
I was terrified by this idea
كنت مرتعبا من هذه الفكرة
that I would lose the ability
التي مفادها أنني سأخسر القدرة
to enjoy and appreciate the sunset
على تمتع وتذوق جمال الغروب
without having my camera on me, without tweeting it to my friends.
دون أن تكون معي كاميرتي ودون أن أكتب تغريدة حولها لأصدقائي.
And it felt like technology
بدا الأمر وكأن التقنية
should enable magic, not kill it.
ينبغي أن تمكننا من القدرة على السحر لا أن تقتله.
When I was a little girl,
عندما كنت طفلة صغيرة،
my grandfather gave me his little silver pocket watch.
أعطاني جدي ساعة جيبه الفضية الصغيرة.
And this piece of 50-year-old technology
وهذه القطعة ذات تقنية عمرها 50 عاما
became the most magical thing to me.
أصبحت أكثر شيء سحري بالنسبة لي.
It became a gilded gateway
أصبحت بوابة مذهّبة
into a world full of pirates and shipwrecks
نحو عالم مليء بالقراصنة وأنقاض السفن
and images in my imagination.
وصور في مخيلتي.
So I felt like our cellphones
لذلك شعرت وكأن هواتفنا الخلوية
and our fancy watches and our cameras
وساعاتنا الفخمة وكاميراتنا
had stopped us from dreaming.
جعلتنا نتوقف عن الحلم
They stopped us from being inspired.
جعلتنا نتوقف عن إمكانية أن نصبح ملهَمين.
And so I jumped in, I jumped into this world of technology,
لذلك قفزت داخل هذا العالم من التقنية،
to see how I could use it to enable magic
لأرى كيفية استغلاله لأصنع الحلم
as opposed to kill it.
عوضاً عن قتله
I've been illustrating books since I was 16.
كنت أضيف الرسومات للكتب منذ كنت في ال 16.
And so when I saw the iPad,
لذلك عندما رأيت الآي باد،
I saw it as a storytelling device
رأيته آداة لرواية القصص
that could connect readers all over the world.
يمكنها أن تصل بين القراء حول العالم.
It can know how we're holding it.
أستطيع معرفة كيفية حمله.
It can know where we are.
أستطيع معرفة أين نتواجد.
It brings together image and text
إنها تجمع الصورة والنص
and animation and sound and touch.
والرسوميات والصوت واللمس.
Storytelling is becoming
أصبح القصّ
more and more multi-sensorial.
متعدد الحواس أكثر فأكثر.
But what are we doing with it?
لكن ماذا نفعل به؟
So I'm actually just going to go in and launch Khoya,
لذلك سأذهب وأطلق "كويا"،
an interactive app for the iPad.
وه تطبيق تفاعلي للآي باد.
So it says, "Place your fingers
حسنا كتب عليها: "ضع أصابعك
upon each light."
فوق كل ضوء."
And so --
وهكذا --
(Music)
(موسيقى)
It says, "This box belongs to ... "
تقول: "هذا المربع ينتمي ل ..."
And so I type in my name.
وهكذا أرقن إسمي.
And actually I become a character in the book.
ثم أصبح في الواقع شخصية في الكتاب.
At various points, a little letter drops down to me --
وفي عدة مرات، يسقط حرف صغير نحوي --
and the iPad knows where you live because of GPS --
ويعرف الآي باد أين تسكن بسبب نظام تحديد المواقع --
which is actually addressed to me.
وهو في الحقيقة يخاطبني.
The child in me is really excited
وابتهج فعلا الطفل بداخلي
by these kinds of possibilities.
لهذه الانواع من الاحتمالات.
Now I've been talking a lot about magic.
كنت اتحدث الآن كثيرا حول السحر.
And I don't mean wizards and dragons,
ولا أعني السحرة والتنانين
I mean the kind of childhood magic,
أقصد نوع سحر الطفولة،
those ideas that we all harbored as children.
تلك الأفكار التي حملناها ونحن أطفال.
This idea of fireflies in a jar, for some reason,
هذه الفكرة حول اليراعات في مرطبان، لسبب ما،
was always really exciting to me.
كانت مثيرة فعلا لي.
And so over here you need to tilt your iPad,
لذلك هنا تحتاج لإمالة الآي باد الخاص بك،
take the fireflies out.
وتخرج اليراعات.
And they actually illuminate your way through the rest of the book.
وسينيرون فعلا طريقك عبر باقي الكتاب.
Another idea that really fascinated me as a child
فكرة أخرى أدهشتني حقا وأنا طفلة
was that an entire galaxy could be contained
كانت في إمكانية احتواء مجرة بأكملها
within a single marble.
ضمن رخامة واحدة.
And so over here,
لذلك هنا
each book and each world
كل كتاب وكل عالم
becomes a little marble
يصبح رخامة صغيرة
that I drag in
ينسحب للداخل
to this magical device within the device.
نحو هذه الآداة السحرية ضمن الآداة.
And it opens up a map.
وتفتح خريطة.
All along, all fantasy books have always had maps,
طوال الوقت، كانت تحوي كل كتب الروايات والاساطير خرائط،
but these maps have been static.
لكن قد كانت هذه الخرائط ساكنة.
This is a map that grows and glows
هذه خريطة تكبر وتتلألأ
and becomes your navigation for the rest of the book.
وتصبح آداة ملاحتك لباقي الكتاب.
It reveals itself to you at certain points in the book as well.
وتكشف نفسها لك في لحظات معينة في الكتاب أيضا.
So I'm just going to enter in.
لذلك سأقوم فقط بالدخول.
Another thing that's actually really important to me
شيء آخر مهم بالفعل لي
is creating content that is Indian
هو خلق محتوى هندي
and yet very contemporary.
ولكن أيضا معاصر جدا.
Over here, these are the Apsaras.
هناك، هؤلاء هم الأبسارات.
So we've all heard about fairies and we've all heard about nymphs,
إذن كلنا سمعنا بالجنيات وسمعنا كلنا بالحوريات.
but how many people outside of India
لكن كم عدد الناس خارج الهند
know about their Indian counterparts, the Apsaras?
الذين يعلمون بنظرائهم الهنديين: الأبسارات؟
These poor Apsaras have been trapped inside Indra's chambers for thousands of years
لقد علق هؤلاء الأبسارات المساكين داخل غرف إندرا لألوف السنين
in an old and musty book.
في كتاب قديم وبال
And so we're bringing them back
إذن إننا نسترجعهم
in a contemporary story for children.
في قصة معاصرة للأطفال.
And a story that actually deals with new issues
وقصة تعالج فعلا قضايا جديدة
like the environmental crisis.
مثل الأزمة البيئية.
(Music)
(موسيقى)
Speaking of the environmental crisis,
بالحديث عن الأزمة البيئية،
I think a big problem has been in the last 10 years
اعتقد أن مشكلة كبيرة تشكلت خلال السنوات ال 10 الماضية
is that children have been locked inside their rooms,
وهو أن الأطفال قد أغلقوا داخل غرفهم،
glued to their PCs, they haven't been able to get out.
ولالتصاقهم بحواسيبهم لم يكن بمقدورهم الخروج.
But now with mobile technology,
لكن الآن مع تقنية الهاتف الجوال،
we can actually take our children outside into the natural world
نستطيع فعلا أخذ أولادنا خارجا نحو العالم الطبيعي
with their technology.
مع تقنيتهم.
One of the interactions in the book
أحد التفاعلات في الكتاب
is that you're sent off on this quest
هي أنك تُبعث في رحلة الاكتشاف هذه
where you need to go outside,
أين تحتاج للخروج،
take out your camera on the iPad
وأخذ كاميرتك في الآيباد
and collect pictures of different natural objects.
وتجمع صورا لأجسام طبيعية مختلفة.
When I was a child, I had multiple collections
عندما كنت طفلا، كان عندي مجموعات مشكّلة مختلفة
of sticks and stones and pebbles and shells.
من عصي وأحجار وحصي وأصداف.
And somehow kids don't do that anymore.
ولسبب ما لا يقوم الأولاد بذلك بعد الآن.
So in bringing back this childhood ritual,
لذلك عند استعادة تقليد الطفولة هذا،
you need to go out
تحتاجون للخروج
and, in one chapter, take a picture of a flower
وفي فصل ما، تلتطقون صورة لزهرة
and then tag it.
ثم وسمها.
In another chapter, you need to take a picture of a piece of bark
في فصل آخر، يجب أن تلتطقوا صورة لقطعة لحاء
And what happens
وما يحدث
is that you actually create a digital collection of photographs
هو أنك في الواقع تصنع مجموعة رقمية من الصور الشمسية
that you can then put up online.
يمكنك بعد ذلك وضعها على النت.
A child in London puts up a picture of a fox
يضع طفل في لندن صورة ثعلب
and says, "Oh, I saw a fox today."
ويقول: "أوه، رأيت اليوم ثعلبا."
A child in India says, "I saw a monkey today."
يقول طفل في الهند: "رأيت اليوم قردا."
And it creates this kind of social network
ويحدث ذلك هذا النوع من الشبكة الاجتماعية
around a collection of digital photographs
حول مجموعة من الصور الشمسية الرقمية
that you've actually taken.
قمتم فعلا بالتقاطها.
In the possibilities of linking together
في احتمالات الربط معا
magic, the earth and technology,
للموسيقى والأرض والتقنية،
there are multiple possibilities.
هناك احتمالات متعددة.
In the next book, we plan on having an interaction
في الكتاب اللاحق، نخطط للحصول على تفاعل
where you take your iPad out with the video on
حيث تحمل الأيباد الخاص بك للخارج والفيديو مشتغل
and through augmented reality,
وعبر الواقع المعزز،
you see this layer of animated pixies
ترى هذه الطبقة من الجنيات المتحركة
appear on a houseplant that's outside your house.
تظهر في نبتة منزلية خارج منزلك.
At one point, your screen is filled up with leaves.
في لحظة ما، تتمتلئ شاشتك بالأوراق.
And so you need to make the sound of wind and blow them away
لذلك يجب أن تقوم بصوت الريح وتزيل الأوراق
and read the rest of the book.
وتقرأ بقية الكتاب.
We're moving, we're all moving here,
إننا ننتقل جميعا، إننا ننتقل جميعا إلى هنا،
to a world where the forces of nature
إلى عالم حيث قوى الطبيعة
come closer together to technology,
تقترب معا أكثر من التقنية،
and magic and technology can come closer together.
ويمكن للسحر والتقنية أن يقتربا أكثر معا.
We're harnessing energy from the sun.
إننا نسخّر الطاقة من الشمس.
We're bringing our children and ourselves
إننا نجلب أولادنا وأنفسنا
closer to the natural world
أقرب للعالم الطبيعي
and that magic and joy
وذلك السحر والفرح
and childhood love that we had
وحب الطفولة الذي لدينا
through the simple medium of a story.
عبر وسيط القصة البسيط.
Thank you.
شكرا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)